Here we have question 4. In scenario 1, a
swimmer
holds a block of mass m at rest in a tank
of
fresh water with density rho 1 as shown in
figure
1. The block is released from rest and
accelerates
upwards with an initial acceleration a.
So that means there would be a net force
going
upwards. In scenario 2, the swimmer holds
the
same block at rest in a tank of salt water
where
density rho 2 is bigger than rho 1.
The swimmer again releases the block from
rest
and the block accelerates upwards with an
initial
acceleration a2. All frictional forces are
negligible.
Indicate whether a1 is greater, equal, or
less
than a2 by writing one of the following in
your
answer booklet. Justify your answer in
terms
of all forces exerted on the block for
each
scenario. Use qualitative reasoning beyond
referencing
equations. Okay, so make sure that in
these types of questions you do not
reference
equations. You have to use reasoning.
In a pool with a greater density, that
means
that there will be more molecules per unit
volume.
So a mass, a block in that pool, there
will
be more molecules below it pushing it up,
which
means that it will have a higher pressure
below
it, which leads to a higher force upwards.
So therefore, the acceleration a2 should
be
bigger than a1. So that would be your
answer.
And what you would say is that a1
is less than a2 because in
a1, in the first scenario, the
density of the
liquid, of the water, is lower than that.
Of the second scenario, so there will be
less
molecules exerting pressure underneath the
first block, leading
to a lower force and a lower acceleration.
And that's all you really need to write,
considering
the general case where a block of mass m
and
a volume v is completely submerged in the
fluid
of density rho. Starting with Newton's
second
law, just derive an expression for the
initial
upward acceleration a of the block where
the
block is released from rest. Express your
answer
in terms of m, v, rho, and physical
constants
as appropriate. Begin your derivation by
writing
a fundamental physics principle or an
equation
from the reference information.
So first of all, what is Newton's second
law
of motion? Well, it states that
acceleration
is proportional to the net force.
And we need to derive an equation for the
term
of acceleration. So Newton's second law,
the
equation for that would be f net
equals mass times the net acceleration.
So the acceleration would then be a equals
f
net over m.
Now what would be the net force?
Well, to do that, we'll have to draw a
free
body diagram. Here would be my mass, and
there
would always be gravity, so this would be
fg
or mg. And the only other force would be
the
buoyant force. Since the block is
accelerating
upwards, that means the buoyant force
should
have a larger magnitude than the gravity
force.
So I would call that fb. So now we can do
the
sum of all forces, the net force would be
equal
to, let's call the upwards direction the
positive
direction and the downwards direction the
negative
direction. So it would be fb minus fg.
We could put that in here, a equals fb
minus
fg over m.
And a would be equal to, well, what is the
force
for buoyancy? Let me just pull that up.
The force for buoyancy is rho vg, where
rho
is the density of the fluid, v is the
volume
displaced, and g is the acceleration due
to
gravity, and fg is simply just mass times
gravity
over m. And I would just factor out g, so
g times rho v minus m over
m, and that would be your net acceleration
initially.
Indicate whether the expression for the
acceleration
a you derived in part b is or is not
consistent
with the claim made in part a, and justify
your
answer referencing your equation. Okay,
this
one is simple, because we know that if
rho,
the density increases, then the
acceleration
increases, because the acceleration is
proportional
to rho v minus m, and if rho increases,
then
rho v minus m increases. So, we would just
write
exactly what I said. Okay, first
of all, you would say yes, it is
consistent
with my claim in part a.
Acceleration in my formula is proportional
to
rho, I'm just going to say p, v minus m.
If the density, rho, increases, then
p, v minus m increases, which leads to
a higher acceleration, and that's really
all
you need to write. And also, I would
mention
that gravity is constant in both cases,
the
volume is constant in both cases, and the
mass
of the block is also constant in both
cases.
And that would be all you would need to
write,
and yeah, that is what I think are the
correct
answers for question 4 of the AP 2025
Physics
I exam. Thank you for watching.